Well, I'm sorry.
Sorry.
I
mean-
Well, yeah. We'll just...
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. Good morning.
Right.
Well, good morning, Jo.
Morning.
And welcome. Obviously, I'm not Catherine.
Yeah.
She's away.
We've got you for two different
things today. We'll start off with the
briefing on your report and upcoming work program, so we'll go till
about 10:30 on that. And then we'll switch
over to
the risk assessment.
9:30 or
10:30?
Oh, sorry, yeah, 9:30. Sorry, my fault.
9:50.
9:50. About 9:50 on that, so 45 minutes.
And so if you want to give us a bit of an introduction and time for questions.
And then we're going to the National Climate-
Three. Yeah
... Engagement-
They do them as two different ones
... so we'll do them.
Yeah, absolutely. And, I believe we have some slides to
be shared. So we're going to take you through-
Perfect
... the monitoring report.
But first I'll just introduce who I've got with me.
Of course, I'm Jo Hendy, the CE of the commission.
And we have Dr. Grant Blackwell, who is the chief scientist at the commission.
And Rob Carr, who is the project director of the
monitoring report. Not to be confused with the previous chair, who
has a D instead of a B. This is Rob.
Yes.
Yeah.
Did note.
It's confused a lot.
Yeah.
Poor guy.
Both excellent.
Yes, of course.
So,
I'm going to just kick off with-
Yep
... some high-level slides, and then Rob is actually going to take
you into the depths of the report. But
if we can
click into the next slide, if that is possible. Brilliant.
In a nutshell, what do we find in this year's emissions
monitoring report? Well, overall risks to
meeting our emissions budgets are growing.
While emissions have been falling, which is a great thing, the progress
is fragile and
the pace is going to need to more than double over the next few
years. So that means government putting in place additional
targeted policies within the next 12 to 24 months.
The good news is that there are more cost-effective
options than even before, and
many of the things that reduce emissions can also bring
down costs and increase resilience for households and
businesses.
But there are barriers in the way of people accessing those benefits,
and this is where policy can be targeted to help reduce
those barriers.
So if we move on to
the next slide, which is a quick recap on our role
here.
So of course, the commission gives independent evidence and advice, but we also
have this independent monitoring role.
And it is designed so government can make well-informed
choices and Parliament has that transparency around the
trade-offs and consequences of different choices.
And it is really designed to provide
predictability and a level of stability through the transition so
that businesses, communities, councils
can act with confidence rather than holding back
under uncertainty.
This year's monitoring report is looking at
the second and third emissions budgets, which are
those five-year caps that are the stepping stones that take emissions
down
towards our 2050 target, and it's also an assessment of what's next to meeting our
2050 target.
So we provide these reports every year, and every year the
government has three months to respond,
and then outline how it intends to
address the recommendations of the commission
This is part of our broader work program.
Earlier this year, we have also given advice on the annual
settings of the desks.
We have provided the National Climate Change Risk Assessment,
and we are about to, in a couple of weeks, provide
the monitoring report on adaptation, which is our
other monitoring role.
The other piece of our work program that's probably relevant
is that
we have kicked off the process for re-updating our
advice on the fourth emissions budget.
And this is in response to the change in the target in the act,
which has triggered us to do a redo of the original advice
we had about the fourth budget, and that's going to be due March next
year. So that's still a few months away.
And finally, just some of the broader context that
we are conscious of in doing this piece of work.
New Zealand is increasingly feeling the impacts of climate
and, of course, in the next session, we'll be talking about
that with the national risk assessment.
At the same time, we've got uncertainty increasing globally.
And we've got
supply chain disruptions, particularly around our fossil fuel supply
chain, while also experiencing that fall in
domestic gas supply.
On the other hand, we have low emissions
technology increasingly available and
affordable, and particularly solar
batteries, heat pumps, and electric vehicles.
So,
pushing in a more optimistic direction on those fronts.
And then finally, why monitoring matters.
Monitoring encourages action.
We've got a similar setup to how a business manages a budget.
Emissions budgets
set out what we need to achieve, what we can spend.
The regular checks allow that course correction, and we have to
anticipate some course correction will be needed because there's always
uncertainty. So by providing
these reports, it creates the transparency and accountability
that helps
increase public trust in the overall system.
I have, as I usually do, forgotten to continue to click through the
slides. But I think with that, you can probably skip the next slide, and I'm going
to hand directly to Rob to actually take you into the nuts and bolts of what we've
found.
Thank you, Jo. So, starting with the progress that we've seen in reducing
emissions. Since 2019, New Zealand's emissions have been falling fairly
steadily by just over 2% a year. And then in the latest year of the
greenhouse gas inventory, we saw that stall, and gross emissions didn't change
significantly in that year. That was largely due to a dry year, which
meant that coal was used to generate electricity.
And in the early data we can see for 2025 so far, it looks like that was
temporary and that reversed out and emissions began declining again.
But it highlights the need for buffers to ensure that we can meet our emissions
goals and that we're not being set back by changes like that.
Digging into the data, we also saw when we looked at industrial emissions,
that a significant reason those have been declining is because of drops in
production rather than the changes in efficiency technology or fuel
switching that we'd want to see for sustained emission reductions that are going to
benefit the economy. We did see in 2024 that net
emissions continued to fall due to forest planted in earlier years that continued
to remove carbon from the atmosphere at greater rates.
So we still saw a fall in net emissions for that year.
The pace of emission reductions now that we're moving into future budgets needs to
roughly double in order to ensure that we can meet our emissions goals.
And that means that,
if additional action does not occur in the next one to two years, it's not going to
be feasible to meet the 2030 biogenic methane target or the third
emissions budget. Those both need work in order to set up for us to achieve
those reductions.
Going to the next slide, please.
Overall, we find that climate risks and the risks to meeting emissions
budgets are growing. This is especially the case for agriculture,
electricity generation, and transport.
The New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme is also not efficiently driving emission
reductions currently.
The second emissions
budget is at significant risk, and it's now too late to plant
additional forests in order to meet any shortfalls in that budget.
So addressing those risks requires greater steps to reduce gross emissions in
those periods to address those risks.
The gap in the emissions reduction plan for the third emissions budget has not been
significantly addressed since our last report, and the risks to some of the planned
reductions in those areas have grown.
And that means we consider current plans insufficient to meet the third emissions
budget and further work is required in that space.
These risks are assessed as at 1st of April, and there has been some further policy
changes by the government since then that could help reduce emissions.
Those are something that we'll consider more fully in next year's report, but we
have noted those where we can through the report this year.
Moving on to the next slide. Around policy changes, the government has taken
or signaled some policy changes that would help reduce emissions in the last
year. However, those are likely to be outweighed by other changes that could cause
emissions to increase.
We've signaled the most significant changes to policy on the slide here and in the
findings of the report, and then in the individual chapters, we track at a more
detailed level the individual policy changes relevant to that area, if you're
interested in getting into those.
As noted before, there have been
some since the 1st of April, and we've noted those in the introduction chapter
and the more significant ones in our findings.
We also note that the ministry merger, the Maori Climate
Platform's funding cycle ending, and the merger of Crown Research Institutes may
also have implications for Maori-Crown relations and
recognition of mātauranga Māori in decision-making that need to be considered in
addition to their climate impacts.
Turning to predictions.
Government projections show that the 2030 biogenic methane target would not be
met. At the moment, it's showing a 7.9% reduction in
emissions by 2030 rather than the 10% target that the government's
aiming for.
And as shown earlier,
predictions also don't show the third emissions budget being met, even if they are
achieved at the moment.
In addition, in some areas around agricultural technology, forests
on Crown land, and landfill gas capture, we've got
concerns that the assumptions underlying those projections don't appear to be
driven by a realistic assessment of current policy, and there would be further
policy work needed in order to ensure that those could be met.
We've recommended the government update its approach in these areas to ensure that
projections remain robust. And that's important to ensure that the
commission and the government are able to accurately monitor if the government is
on track to meet emissions budgets.
And it's also important for the stability of the New Zealand Emissions Trading
Scheme, because we rely on those projections in order to set the emissions cap
for that.
We've taken a closer look at two of the examples of opportunities this year, if you
go to the next slide, please,
to understand the business case for them better.
So the first one is around industrial heating.
So businesses who use fossil fuels for heat,
using an electric heat pump is now generally cheaper for them below 100
degrees. Heat pumps are on average 39% cheaper than
coal and 54% cheaper than gas for their running costs, and that
means even for someone with an existing boiler, changing that out before end of
life, the running cost saving is likely to outweigh the capital cost
of making that change for a business.
Biomass can also now be cheaper than coal or gas across the temperature
range, including in those higher heat scenarios, and that's particularly the case
if businesses have access to hog fuel or wood chip locally that can enable them to
use that at low cost. Emissions in 2035 could be up to
three megatons lower if we achieved faster decarbonization
of non-transport energy through taking up opportunities like these.
Next slide, please.
Can we ask questions as we go through this or is the-
Well, how many-
I've got questions. There's questions already. So, yeah.
Well, we're nearly through. We'll work our way through and then we can come back to
it.
Yeah.
That's the simplest. Yeah. And, uh-
I'm hardly used to it here. I'm sorry.
David, I'll put you down for a question. That ear thing.
Western.
Carry on.
Okay.
Sorry.
So, next slide on electric vehicles and transport,
while switching to public transport or active transport will often be the cheapest
option for people, they're not always a practical option.
But we are seeing that electric vehicles are increasingly becoming cost
competitive. So while they cost more up front, they more than pay for themselves in
lower fuel and maintenance costs, in some cases after only five years.
For compact SUVs, which are the most common family car that people buy
new in New Zealand, an electric vehicle owner could save around
$7,500 on average over five years in running costs.
So they're saving over $1,000 a year on their running cost by making that
switch. And greater adoption of electric vehicles could
mean emissions in 2035 are up to 3.1 megatons lower
than currently projected.
Moving to the next slide, please. So the obvious question is, if it's cheaper, why
is policy needed?
And the key pieces there are upfront costs and people's ability to
finance that is often a major barrier.
Mm-hmm.
So both individuals and businesses may see the real benefits for them to access
those technologies, but they don't have the cash flow to make that change
currently. Split incentives can also be a major issue.
For example, where the landlord needs to pay for the upgrade, but it's the tenant
that gets the benefit of it. There's also data gaps or people feeling
like they have unclear signals about what choice they should make that play a role
in people's decision-making. And sometimes there are system-level shifts that are
needed, where people need the infrastructure to be in place before they can make
the change.
These barriers are preventing people from taking up some of these opportunities,
and they can be removed in many cases at little or no financial cost to the
government as well, while failing to address them can cost the government and the
economy more in other ways.
Turning to the next slide around what needs to happen next.
There are sufficient opportunities, many of them low cost for the government to
ensure that emissions budgets are met, and the main areas of risk that we've
highlighted are also generally the main areas of opportunity where we could achieve
further emission reductions. The time available to course correct for those future
targets is now short. Many emission reductions depend on the
decisions made well before reductions are realized, and some options for the
second emission budget are already no longer available.
This increases the importance of taking action now, where there are barriers,
delays, or weak incentives preventing people from making progress.
We've recommended the government take additional action within the next year to
ensure it can meet its emissions goals, and we've sought to highlight the key
actions that the government can take that would make the biggest difference to
reduce emissions and the risks that the country faces through the recommendation
that we've made. And those are to start determining now how to
incentivize further emission reductions and removals in the 2030s,
given that the emissions trading scheme will struggle to do this in its current
form.
For the primary sector, immediately scale up support to ensure that the 2030
biogenic methane target can be met, and to reduce barriers for
long-term low emissions agricultural products for long-term
reductions in resilience.
And waste, to expand resource recovery facilities, services, and planning, and to
extend landfill gas capture requirements to Class
II landfills.
In transport, to encourage electric vehicle uptake through both
strong supply and demand side measures there, and also to support greater shifts
to public and active transport,
and to address the upfront cost barriers and energy for fuel switching for
households and businesses.
Next slide, please. So now that our report is finished, the next steps sits with
the government, so they have three months to
do to address the risks and opportunities
available. Policy choices sit with them.
So this is the opportunity to course correct and make sure budgets are met.
And you can find more information about our report on our website.
So we both have short summaries for you to get into the particular sector that
you're interested in. A full report for those who want to read all the findings.
And we do also have a technical annex and supporting spreadsheets for people who
want to get into greater levels of detail or dig through the data as well.
And with that, we're very happy to answer your questions.
Right. Well, that's good. Right then, we've got questions of Deborah
Russell, and David, do you have a question?
Yep.
Yep, and then I'll come to Lana.
Okay. Lots and lots and lots to ask about.
So-
We'll just-
I'll just-
You'll hear a couple and then we'll just-
I was going to say, keep on adding me to the bottom of your list.
All right, Deborah. I guess I got the message.
Think of the economy.
The rest of us might get a turn.
No, I just wanted to add to the bottom of the list.
No, thank you. No, I'm hearing you.
Look,
it's a little hard to know where to start. Let's start with the most obvious one.
Can we meet our second emissions budget if we take action
now?
Yes.
Okay.
Absolutely.
Our third emissions budget?
Yes.
Would those be emissions reductions if we take action now that are
gross emissions reductions? Can we reduce our gross emissions, not just our
net emissions?
Yes. So as, Rob, maybe you want to
explain a bit more of the context around it.
Yes. So for our second emissions budget, we've now passed the
window where we can plant forestry to meet that budget.
It takes four to six years from when you first plant a tree till it starts
absorbing meaningful amounts of carbon.
So,
for the second emissions budget, it's too late for forestry, but for the third
emissions budget, if the government wants to meet that using forestry, it needs to
plant those trees now in the next few years, and there needs to be the incentives
in place to do that. For gross emission reductions, there's still lots of
opportunities where we could reduce our gross emissions further through to the end
of the second emissions budget.
The key sort of considerations to think about in that space is we want to
make a large change to industrial emissions to,
take for example, the New Zealand Steel electric arc furnace.
That's taken three years from it starting to being able to
deliver its emission reductions.
So you need to allow enough lead time for those to come through, and that means we
need that
in place by the start of the third emissions budget to achieve those reductions,
but there's still opportunities you can access during the second emissions budget
period.
And the other
significant point to note in terms of timing is for the New Zealand Emissions
Trading Scheme,
we think to get through that change in sort of a stable way that's
going to bring the market along with it, that's a reform that needs to happen
slowly over time. And so you want to start it now and work on it over the
next few years to make sure that it's in place,
in a safe period before we reach that point where unit supply and demand
don't line up in the 2030s. So that's a
process that needs to start now, but is something that should happen gradually over
time.
So,
thank you. You've said something there I just want to pursue a little bit further
straightaway, which is around the ETS.
So we know it's in a fragile state, I think that's the words you used in your...
I'm trying to read some of those. I was powering through.
If we start adjusting the ETS now, will that send
sufficient signals, do you think
to...
Do we need to have positive government action rather than just relying on the ETS
to drive meeting the 2030 target?
The first, second emissions target.
So we've recommended, as you know, the starting that process
around the ETS, that process needs to be inclusive and
well-paced so that
participants in the ETS-
Yep
... have an opportunity to reflect how it might impact them,
so that you maintain market confidence in the change.
That needs to happen, but additional policies outside the
ETS are needed to target those barriers
to get us on track for the second budget.
Okay, so I've got to parse that in. So the ETS on its own is not
sufficient to meet the second emissions budget.
Correct.
Thank you. That's what I understood.
I just wanted to make sure I had it right in my head.
Okay,
I want to go to something new.
I'll give you this one, then we'll move for another if that's okay, Deborah.
Sure. All good. No worries, Grant.
No, I-
Appreciate that. No worries. I wanted to go to the projections
slide.
This one here. And your recommendation was, and this
is one I found a bit confusing, said, "Update the approach to emissions
projections
so they give a robust, realistic signal of likely future policy
impact." And that just,
it struck me a little bit oddly.
Are we going to try to fix the projections or are we going to try to fix the
underlying climate policy?
Yeah. So, this is a bit of a different issue-
Yeah. Oh, okay
... to the climate policy. This is about the evidence that's been
used to underlie
the settings of the ETS and climate policy more
broadly.
Good decisions need to be based on robust predictions.
Yeah.
We have identified some issues with the current government
projections where we've found insufficient evidence
to back up some of those assumptions.
So what we have specifically recommended here is an
improvement of that process.
So these are the projections that are coming out of, I don't want to finger
people because that seems mean, but out of MFE or what was
MFE, it's now MCERT?
Yeah. The broader ministries that are involved in
creating these projections. Rob, did you want to elaborate?
Yeah. So, MCERT coordinates the projections
overall, but each government agency is responsible for
producing the underlying projections and assumptions related to their specific
area. So for
forestry and for agriculture, that's the Ministry for Primary
Industries, while for waste, that's MCERT itself.
So you're in effect saying that
the data and the processes that
MPI is using are not
good enough to give us good projections.
So
when we say that projected 7.9% from government, you're saying
actually we can't really... We should regard that figure
as a-
Not as certain as it looks.
Yes.
I'm trying my best-
So we're concerned-
Trying to phrase this nicely, so I'm not going to go and say
We're concerned even that 7.9% may be-
Optimistic
... overly optimistic.
Yeah.
But for agricultural
technology, the main issue is actually after 2030.
So up to
2030, it follows the standard
approach to development projections, and then after 2030 it outlines three
scenarios, and the one that the government has used as a central scenario
relies on some expansion of industry incentives or government
policy to achieve current industry targets.
And that hasn't been committed to yet.
Right.
And when it comes to-
Yeah
... projections, what we want to see is for everything that's included within
that to have a clear, defined policy that is going to achieve
that projection. Where there's things that we'd sort of like to do, but we're
still working out the details, that's better to recognize as a gap that further
policy needs to be developed for.
So it's not a measurement issue per se, but it's to do with...
Although I'm sure that there's ongoing difficulties with getting our measurements
right, but more to do with how certain policies are. Yeah.
Yes.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you. Right. Rob, Sup, yeah.
Yeah.
And then Mark. Just to sup on that. So, but you're talking about the assumptions
that go to the projections for both policy setting and
also the ETS, and you frame that as two different things.
Can you just take us through
the differences for the ETS versus
the other?
Yeah. Sure. So,
to work out what the unit limits and
price controls are for a five-year period, part of
that methodology takes into account the
projections which allow
assessing what the cap within the ETS essentially
needs to be. So if those are not robust,
then you're potentially setting up an issue with the
settings that you determine for the ETS.
So Rob, did you want to go into...?
Yeah. So I guess the primary
issue there is if you have overly optimistic
agricultural projections, because they're not in the emissions trading scheme,
if you then get to the period and those reductions aren't
achieved, you then very rapidly need to find emission reductions
within the emissions trading scheme covered sectors.
And so that can cause volatility within the scheme and means you might get
reductions in your energy sectors in a way that's undesirable, where they're
reducing production rather than making the sort of changes that you'd want to see
because they had a longer lead time to make those changes.
So you want to make sure that the projections are robust and give you a clear
picture of what that split between the different sectors is likely to be for
setting those emissions trading scheme settings.
Right. And you said in your opening that these weren't realistic,
and you've said now a couple of times that they're overly optimistic, and so that
goes to the reporting around the agricultural
issues that's been in the media
recently.
Yeah. So we think it is possible to achieve that level of emission reduction, but
it would require further action to do so.
And that's the thing that we have to ensure, if something's going to go into the
projections, you need that certainty about what those
actions are going to be first.
Can I have a sup or grab a sup on that particular point there?
So what actions are you talking about?
So it depends on the sector somewhat.
But for agriculture, there's an
assumption that there'll be some sort of incentive
coming further that would enable farmers to adopt technologies at greater
rates. And so the projections have within them quite high
uptake of technologies like methane inhibitors.
Mm-hmm.
And you wouldn't see that without some sort of incentive in place
for the farmers to adopt that or really clear demonstrator productivity benefits.
And so there'd need to be some sort of
What do you base that last comment on?
That's what we hear consistently from the sector.
So,
for farmers, in order to adopt those technologies,
they don't necessarily
directly
receive a payment from a direct customer for the emission reduction they receive.
Mm.
Their products go into a larger pool that goes out through the processes-
Mm-hmm
... and then to customers. And there needs to be
some financial reward for the farmer for adopting that-
You mean like the cooperative difference scheme that they've got in place now?
Yes.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Blair.
Yeah. Thank you. I just wanted to pick up on your comments about
what I'm hearing you say is basically when there's
too optimistic assumptions in the agricultural sector
particularly,
the volatility gets passed on to other sectors.
Is that what you're saying? If we are still
apparently committed to meeting our budgets and our targets,
is that what you're saying?
That's one element.
For the non-biogenic methane sectors
to meet the budgets, it gets transferred via the ETS.
Okay. Thank you. And then, so you've given us some really clear
examples using agriculture. What are the
other assumptions and projections specifically that
you're referring to, like, across the other sectors?
Yeah. So the other two relate to forestry on
Crown land and landfill gas capture.
So for forestry on Crown land, this was also an issue that we highlighted in
last year's report that the way that that projection was
built was to look at what would be needed to achieve a
five-megatonne reduction in 2050, and then to gap fill from there-
Mm-hmm
... how many trees would we need to plant to achieve that, and
then look to find the policy in order to achieve that number of trees.
Later, and our concern was those projections may be overly optimistic
as to how many trees could be planted or how much land would be available on Crown
land that would be suitable for forestry to achieve those projections.
In landfill gas capture,
there's been projections in the last two years for improved
efficiency and uptake of landfill gas captures by
landfills. And the government signaled that
it would do a review of policy in that space, but hadn't outlined
what the policy measures it would do to achieve those assumptions.
Since we have published our report, MCERT has now released a consultation
document which outlines some proposals that they could put in
place that would help reduce landfill gas capture
emissions, and those would go some way to achieving the assumptions that are
set out on the projections currently, but wouldn't necessarily achieve all of
them if they were implemented.
Mm-hmm.
Supplementary.
About the forestry sup.
Yeah.
I was looking here when you're talking about the no capacity for additional
forestry planting and thinking that's coming from NPI.
I wondered what assessment had been done on some of the work like re-cloaking
Papatuarnuku and so on, where
the reduction of browsers, whether it's possums or an
overload-
Deer
... of deer and so on, makes quite a big difference.
And whether, because then you're not talking about the
little trees, you're talking about the big trees-
Correct
... coming back to health. And I just wondered where that was in any of the
forestry discussions, because I don't think it's exactly
NPI's area.
Yeah.
The government has yet to confirm how it will treat
forest management emissions within the emissions budgets.
So for the national contribution, it has set a forest
reference level, and it signaled that it would look to apply that in some way
to emissions budgets, but it doesn't directly apply because they cover different
time periods, and it hasn't
set out yet exactly how that will be achieved.
We've set out a bit more detail on that within the areas for attention in the
forestry chapter that goes through the issues in that space a little bit more.
But, the rules that affect-
About native forestry.
About-
Or native forest
... about how
we improve the carbon stored in existing forests.
The rules for that haven't been locked down yet-
Let me nail you
... in those budgets.
But there are some recommendations on their way or
kind of?
That's a policy piece that the government's working through.
They haven't confirmed their approach yet.
Okay. They've started.
Right. We'll go primary question, David.
Yes.
Which I'll hold.
Final sup.
Final sup. No more sups on this topic.
Yeah, just
because we're hearing these-
And also
... overly optimistic projections.
Can you just help the committee understand, you get this
information given to you.
Mm-hmm.
Is there some sort of back and forth even in
your work and understanding it, where you're sort of saying to
the agencies, "Hey,
are these
relevant and pragmatic and all that?"
What has been the response in that process, if any?
Or is it very like they just give you the data, you do your
assessment? How does that work?
So we do engage at a working level on evidence and modeling,
and we have an MoU set out between us and the
agencies to-
... to make clear the distinction between that
and our independent assessment. So those conversations
happen.
But ultimately, and that helps us understand
more why they've made certain decisions.
But then we go away and independently assess
whether this meets sufficient standards-
Mm-hmm
... and then report back
via our formal report.
Thank you.
And right, David.
Thanks.
One of your pages
demonstrated the conversion or the gains to be made
converting to electrification.
Mm-hmm.
Particularly boilers, I think is what the example was, and it had a capital
component to the cost of the electric boilers.
But from my experience, there's many companies that
wish to transfer.
The capital cost of the equipment is one component, and often a very
small component of the total capital cost of
particularly getting the electricity to sites.
And how have you taken account-
Transmission
... of the practicality of the transition in those situations?
Yes. Yeah, no, so that's a very good point.
It is very site specific, but there can be big barriers
around that connection cost. So that's one of the other barriers that
we've pointed to in the report.
Did you want to add anything there, Rob?
Yes. No, that's absolutely the case.
So that capital figure on that slide is all the
part that's within the business end.
It doesn't cover the lines cost if someone needs to have a substantial build
to them.
Where someone
doesn't need a significant lines
upgrade, then switching an existing fossil
fuel boiler that is not end of life yet can be
economic.
Where they do need a substantial lines upgrade, it will be case dependent, but
in those cases, if the boiler is end of life, it's still often going to be
economic even with those lines charge upgrades costs factored in.
Okay. So there's the, when you call it a lines
charge, it's actually two parts. There's a capital-
Right
... applied by the EDBs or the network owners.
But there are actually line charges, and currently we're in the middle of the
DPP4 with regards to their spend, and
they're
well north of $10 billion.
Mm-hmm.
And we've got the RCP with regards to Transpower, which is well north of
$5 billion. And that's equating into the power bills
of all consumers, including industrial
and commercial. And even though I think we're making
strides with reducing the electricity tariff- rate
down. In fact, the futures are indicating that quite substantially at the moment.
It's said that the lines charges are actually going to almost
nullify that any effect coming through.
So there's the capital outlay of improving the lines component,
increasing the pipe to get it there, but there's also the fact that the actual
tariff or the cost of the electricity and lines charges
is not actually helping the situation either.
Yeah. Correct, and I think this also highlights the importance of
the broader electricity system keeping
pace with what we need.
Yeah.
There's issues around the flexibility,
the backup and storage that can really help.
Yeah.
But while we're making a lot
of strides in building more renewable generation, that system
needs to keep pace-
Yeah
... yeah, so we can make the most of it.
Yeah.
Lan, you going to sup on it?
Not a sup.
No, it's not a sup, right.
We'll go
Joseph.
Oh, thank you. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Look, I'm interested in the intersection between the domestic budgets and the
NDC,
and because obviously there's some intersection to a degree.
Mm-hmm.
And just going back to the
2021 target, which was to reduce
2030 emissions by 50% on 2005
levels.
Mm-hmm.
And the advice that Treasury gave that more than 70% of those emission units would
have to come from offshore.
Mm.
From what they said was markets that didn't exist, and therefore costs that were
unknowable.
Mm-hmm.
And I'm interested in how this works through to the work you're doing, the advice
you're providing now.
Because if more than 70% of emission units have to come from offshore according to
Treasury itself-
Mm-hmm
...
what is your view on that?
Yeah, so this work here is domestic focused.
We don't give advice on the NDC unless we're specifically requested via the act and
the minister. So just putting that aside.
Cool.
The NDC was
set originally with the idea that it would
need to be met through a mix of domestic and offshore
mitigation. There is scope to
do more domestically.
Mm-hmm.
There is not sufficient scope to close the gap
entirely.
And so this is a place where how the
gap is met
needs to be clearly articulated by the government.
That's not our role to provide advice on that unless we're asked.
Sure. So you've never provided any advice on
either disputing or agreeing with Treasury's analysis of more than 70% of emission
units have to come from offshore?
We have
provided advice specifically on
NDC1 and NDC2 in response to ministerial requests.
We've also, in
pieces of work, provided some calculations to help
give a sense of scale. We've never, beyond that, from
memory, provided any
further advice on that gap. But Rob,
do you have anything to add on that?
No, our advice has been limited to what the domestic contribution towards those
nationally determined contributions could be.
We haven't looked at the international component or been asked to in the advice
that we've provided.
I guess what I'd add on to
Joe's point is if the government does choose to take actions to
overachieve the second emissions budget, that would help reduce any offshore
mitigation that might be required for the first nationally determined contribution.
For the second nationally determined contribution, that one has been roughly
aligned to the third emissions budget, and so ensuring that we stay on track
for that budget ensures that we don't need to make any offshore contribution in
order to meet that nationally determined contribution for that period.
Okay, thanks. So just last confusion.
Sure, yeah.
So just,
you're purely focused on the domestic emission budget and
the international component of the NDC is not within your
remit.
Unless we're asked.
Unless you're specifically asked.
Yeah. That's right.
Okay. Thanks.
Right. Primary from, okay, I've got from Lan, and then I see that you
have a primary. Okay, right, Lan.
Yeah, I'm really interested in your comment on
page 30.
Government actions to reduce emissions in the last year are likely to be
outweighed by other actions that may increase them.
What actions specifically are you referring to with
this? And I'm particularly interested in our resource management
bills have just come back from this committee to government,
which don't have a clear framework of climate mitigation.
Has any of that been
included in your report at all? Can you help us understand that?
Yes, so
within the report we sort of sort things into categories, what we think is likely
to increase or decrease, and so that's set out in our findings chapter and
on the slide earlier in terms of highlighting the main contributors there.
In terms of the Resource Management Act reform, that's one that we've signaled
may have an unclear impact on emissions.
So, through the fast track, there's been a large number of
renewable developments consented through that process, and
consent remains a major barrier for
getting some of the electricity changes that we need and
enabling businesses to decarbonize.
So where those investments can be prioritized through resource
management reforms, that will help us reduce our emissions into the future and
lower the cost of the transition as well, and there has been some work in that
space that would support emission reductions there.
But then some of those reforms to the Resource Management Act
also carry the potential to also expedite consent processes for
things that could increase emissions.
And so you have a risk on that side as well that you could see things that offset
those gains that you get in your energy sector from faster consenting.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you. And then, so-
Do you understand,
internationally, how other countries are
approaching their emissions budgets and
targets? Are there countries who
have managed to have a national
level ETS or similar, and
basically ignored the domestic path in terms of
urban development, transport corridor?
Because that's our government's approach at the moment.
They're saying, "The emissions trading scheme is going to drive
our emissions reductions," when clearly we're seeing that's
going to be
failed to do so.
Absolutely.
So yeah. How do we compare internationally with how other
countries are approaching
this huge challenge?
So internationally, generally,
emissions pricing and emissions trading schemes are increasing.
So they're increasingly
covering more and more emissions globally.
And at the same time, their jurisdictions are generally
also employing
other targeted policies to deal with the non-price barriers.
So, a number of the barriers we raised
previously. A
good example might be
the UK, for example,
or we have the Europe ETS, European ETS as
well, that has been running longer than our ETS.
Rob, do you want to add anything?
Yeah. I'll just add, whilst the emissions trading scheme is a really
important tool for reducing our emissions, it doesn't cover the majority of the
economy, so it does need additional support mechanisms for those
parts it doesn't cover, in addition to addressing those
barriers that Jo raised. In
some of those other sectors that are ETS covered, New
Zealand started from a better place than a lot of other countries with high
levels of renewable electricity generation.
But we haven't made the same progress as other countries have
made in electrifying our economy and
decarbonising our use of energy outside of that, as some of those other countries
have made that have used more active tools in order to
drive that change. So the example being for electric vehicles,
our rate of purchasing
new electric vehicles last year was around 11%, while the
global average was around 25%.
Mm-hmm.
So we're actually behind, not just other developed countries, but some
developing countries that are moving ahead in their electric vehicle
decarbonization in that space. And that's because they've put in place
strong systems of
vehicle standards and upfront support for costs
that have enabled them to achieve high levels of uptake.
Yeah. I've got a couple subs on that.
But first, I heard you say before, so you're saying the fast track processes
helped speed up the whole renewable electricity generation
in the country? It's constructive.
I'm just curious, the commentary around, my understanding is that
in Europe and possibly even in Britain, they're slowing down some of their
processes through the ETS, and impacts because of the impacts on
their economy. Is that the case? Have there
been any signs of that from those economies in terms of where they
approach their climate change targets?
The EU and UK continue to-
Mm-hmm
... expand their policy measures over time.
They do have back and forths, as every country does-
Mm-hmm
... in moving things, but their general trend over time has been
to continue
their decarbonization journey, and both of them
are seeking greater levels of emission reduction than New Zealand does from their
targets.
Okay. Who's next? We have Celia.
Thank you.
I've got a question on the landfill area in your
recommendation one. And
it's quite high up the priorities.
Can you talk a little bit about how the Waste Management
Act is or isn't making a difference there?
Is there enough levy coming back to local authorities to make them do
things, or does the bit that goes to central government, has there
been enough investment in
sort of national research that helps those?
Most landfills are local authority, not all.
Yes. So overall, in waste, the
government's primary tool there is the Waste
Minimization Fund, and that funds projects on a case-by-case
basis for reducing emissions. And the government's notes on
its projections itself notes that that doesn't address the
broader need to transform the system.
So,
it helps get individual projects across the line that can help reduce emissions,
but to achieve large levels of organic waste disposal, we
need a more
strategic look across the sector to address the infrastructure deficit that's
in place there. And to make sure that we've got the whole system
functioning as a system,
to make sure that we're getting the levels of waste diversion needed.
The government's also been taking action to improve the uptake
of landfill gas capture,
and that is
very useful for
capturing emissions. But there are other alternatives like anaerobic
digestion and composting that can reduce emissions
by more. And
anaerobic digestion also has benefits like providing
digestate to the agriculture sector, or gas for
energy use that can help support the economy in other ways as well.
And those other alternatives aren't being given the same sort of
treatment that might enable them to be taken up at scale.
And would that
Um, direction or more comprehensive approach, which would
include local government. Would that be led by MCERT or-
They're the primary agency-
Yeah
... responsible in that space.
Okay.
Think, yeah, last question, Deborah.
Oh.
We're at 9:50 and we're switching topics.
So much for-
Same.
But you've got two minutes.
Okay, well, yeah.
Be quick.
I'm intrigued, you said that we've been reducing our emissions by about 2% a
year, but at present, that seems to be-
... related to the fact that basically the economy has been on a downwards
process for the last couple of years.
Are you concerned that,
when at some date the economy starts to pick up again, we will see emissions
increasing again?
That is a risk.
Yeah.
And you can already see that to some extent in the
agricultural sector, where we're getting higher
dairy and meat prices currently, and that's going to feed through
to
greater emissions there if we don't have the technologies coming in to support them
to reduce their emissions at the same time.
Yeah.
And so-
At the moment.
Yes.
Yeah. I've talked to-
That's right, Karen
... I've talked to those people too. I know this stuff's coming.
Look, I do want to go to a slightly different-
Can I, can I have a supplement?
Well, I have-
Yeah, Deborah
... I do. I do want to go to something slightly different, though, in this area,
though, and I'm concerned about process heat.
So I was meeting with the brewers actually last week, and they said that they were
rapidly electrifying throughout brewing, because they could.
They didn't need that high level of process heat.
Mm-hmm.
But we have some areas where you've just got to have
process heat, which needs fossil fuels to get the required levels of heat.
So, what I'm concerned, I guess I'm worried about the extent to which there's
process heat in our economy that we can't
get rid of, and we have to then try to
use trees to offset and things like that.
So how's that worked into your modeling?
Are you thinking in terms, yeah, of what could be done and what government- ...
could do?
Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. And we do make that differentiation between low temperature
process heat and high temperature process heat.
Yeah.
Um,
Mark, do you-
Yeah. There can be solutions for those high temperature process heat
situations as well. So biomass can be a really good
option in some of those cases where they've got the local supply that can enable
them to use them, and it comes at a reasonable cost.
Goldman Cement is using old tires to
fuel their furnace. And
green hydrogen may be an option for some options.
There's some work going on for building a plant using steel production, using
green hydrogen at the moment. It provides an option in that space.
But in that high heat scenario, it may be that that's a journey that does need
to take some time for some of those businesses.
If we're
helping support all those businesses that have low temperature process heat
needs to move onto electricity, that will free
up gas supply for those low temperature
users to continue to use that until there is a viable transition
option for them available.
Right. Okay, let's stop there, team.
We've-
Thank you
... thank you. Thanks very much. Right, we're now going to move on to the next, the
National Climate Change Risk Assessment.
Okay.
Put another hat on then.
Yeah, yeah, that's right. Remember what I'm talking about?
Righto.
Cool, so we are swapping people around a little bit.
Yeah. Yep.
So Grant is going to stay.
I'll introduce Dr. Karen Levin, who is the General
Manager of Evidence and Advice. And we also
have one of our experts from our team, and Ellie and Aseton
are there to help answer
the nuts and bolts if we get into that.
But we're going to start again with a-
Yep
... presentation-
Slideshow
... that also has some maps in it. So hopefully-
Go for it
... we can
dive into some detail there. So, but first I wanted to start by acknowledging
the committee's past and current work on adaptation,
including opening the inquiry into adaptation, the important
role you play in maintaining the Climate Change Response Act
architecture and providing that
cross-party scrutiny.
If we move into a few slides from
me, then I'm going to pass to Grant and then Karen, who will go into
depth. But first, just to recap on why this matters.
Of course, in recent times, we've just seen how devastating
more extreme weather has been. 15 years ago, we were having a
extreme, a severe, significant weather event once a
month, and now in the last 18 months, it's been about once every
eight days. So it's telling us climate change is not something off in the
future. It is,
we're experiencing now. And it is reshaping the hazards
that we, um, natural hazards that we have long lived with, but it's
increasing their frequency, severity, and
unpredictability. And events like Cyclone
Gabrielle showed us not just the immediate
impacts on communities and emergency services, but also that longer
term disruption that flows through onto food production, onto
businesses, onto ecosystems. So it is no longer
natural hazard management BAU. Um,
climate change is shifting what we think of as normal.
Mm.
And that means our systems need to adapt in
response. And while we've been seeing a lot of effects
of flooding in recent times, this is more than just flooding.
The risk assessment that we're about to show you considers a wide
range of climate hazards, including event-based hazards
like extreme weather, wildfires, and landslides.
But also the ongoing and progressive changes that kind
of sneak up on you, like sea level rise or
changing temperatures.
Most of us are used to thinking about risk as likelihood times
impact. And also with climate change, it is easy
to jump straight from the natural hazard, the
flood, the fire, the drought, and think of that as if it is the risk.
But actually, climate risk is the result of those
hazards meeting people, places, infrastructure,
ecosystems or our services that are exposed and
vulnerable.
So that's why it's important to look at this in a framework of the natural hazard,
the exposure and the vulnerability.
That shows you where your levers are as a
government in Parliament and people more broadly.
So, global emissions reductions limit how
severe the other hazards become. Planning
choices affect what is exposed. And
then resilience infrastructure, social support,
preparedness affect how badly people and
systems are hit, and how well they recover.
The National Climate Change Risk Assessment is not an
operational risk assessment, it is strategic at that national level.
It's like a national warrant of fitness, essentially.
And the intent is really to help decision-makers focus
on where
from that national picture, the risk is highest and the impacts are
greatest, so that you can
prioritize coordinated action where it will make the
biggest difference. And of course, prioritization means we can
act sooner on the most important issues.
And the sooner we act, the more we strengthen resilience, protect the things we
rely on every day, and get the country out of what we are currently
in, which is a cycle of react and recover.
Mm.
So looking over the last 15 years at what the
central government has spent on natural hazards,
97% has gone into response and
recovery, and only 3% on reducing future risk.
Now, of course, local government will
spend money on risk reduction as well, so that's not the entire
picture. But it really does point to
a balance of where our effort has been.
And it's not to say response and recovery aren't important. They really are.
But it's about shifting that balance.
We're currently paying for the costs of
these extreme events, and the
events of 2023 showed us, for example,
the government needing to pay direct costs of 6.6
billion, total damages of around 14 billion.
And then, of course, there's the knock-on effects to the economy,
and social effects more broadly that aren't counted in those
numbers.
Proactive adaptation
can really pull us out of this spiral.
For every dollar that is invested in proactive
adaptation, up to $10 can be saved in
terms of reducing future damages.
So this is where we want to get to.
BAU hazard management is not going to be enough for the scale of
adaptation needed.
Mm.
And so the assessment that we're going to talk to you shows where that focused,
coordinated action will make the biggest difference.
And with that, I'm going to pass to Grant, I believe,
to take us through the next set of slides.
Jo.
Next slide, please, and if Jo has clicked. Ah, yeah, no, that's me.
So good morning, everyone. I've got three slides, sort of a story in three
parts. I really just wanted to spend a bit of time talking about sort of the
science that underpins the risk assessment and how we've thought about the science
as we've gone about that assessment.
So the first
point is really around sort of certainty and uncertainty.
There's always uncertainty in everything that we do.
And we need to think about that when we're also thinking about the science.
So two things can be true at the same time.
So the science of climate change itself is well understood.
We know that some gases trap heat. We know
how the greenhouse gases work. We know that
as gases increase in the atmosphere, more heat is trapped.
That makes the atmosphere warmer, that makes the oceans warmer.
We know how that plays it physically to affect ocean currents or
rainfall patterns and these sorts of things.
So that basis is well understood and has been well understood for sort of a
century or more. And so as we see emissions
increasing and concentrations increasing, we will see those
climate hazards that Jo talked about, yeah, increasing, so higher
temperatures, more rainfall, more storms, those sorts of things.
So those are well understood. What's less well understood
is how that will play out at a specific place at a specific time in the
future. So we don't know exactly what the temperature will be in Wellington in
2060 or those sorts of things. So there is uncertainty
on exactly how emissions might track and then into the big climate
models, exactly how that might play out to affect temperature patterns and those
sorts of things.
And so that's where we use scenarios and projections.
And just to note, so a projection is basically
something of interest, how it might play out into the future.
So, we were just talking about emissions projections in the
ERM. So that was around projections of emissions from
different sectors, is what we're talking about when we're talking about projections
there. In terms of sort of climate change and climate
risks, then we use scenarios which are
a- Basically thinking about how might emissions
track if different futures play out.
So if we have a whole lot of coordinated action, lots of countries do things, we
have lots of uptake of clean tech, what might global emissions look
like? Or if every country does things a bit differently, what might emissions look
like? Or if
we have no action and we carry on using more and more fossil fuels, what might
emissions look like? And then we can run those through climate models to say, okay,
given those emissions, what might that mean for temperature or for sea level rise
or for drought, these sorts of things.
And so they can give us a range of possible futures that we can
think about. And those scenarios are periodically updated
excuse me, as
we see how action has actually been going,
understanding sort of increases around what emissions are doing, those sorts of
things. Then scientists will look at those and say, okay, we think actually, we'll
refine those scenarios and then the predictions can be run again, updated,
and we can hopefully narrow those windows of what the future might look like.
And so you may have seen some commentary around updates to scenarios leading
up to the next IPCC report and some changes there,
which is a good news and a bad news story.
So initially, the highest scenario that we were looking at, that 8.5
scenario,
the world is not tracking towards that. So that's a good thing.
Emissions are coming down-
Mm
... fast in that scenario. The flip side is none of the scenario, the new scenarios
limit warming to 1.5 degrees. So the world has not done enough to limit warming
to 1.5. So there's that sort of narrowing there.
In terms of the risk assessment, we used two scenarios to look at what the future
might be like for those climate risks.
We used a low warming scenario, which was about two degrees of warming by the end
of the century, and we used a high emissions, high warming scenario, which
was around three to three and a half degrees of warming.
What might our climate risks look like at that sort of range?
So we didn't use that 8.5, that high-
Mm
... high scenario for that work.
If I could have the next slide, please.
So then the second point I just wanted to note is that,
when we're thinking about these climate risks, they generally don't happen in
isolation. Which is sort of obvious if we think about it.
But if we think of a rainfall event that causes some
landslides that block a road. So that road has been
damaged, but the community's on the other side of that road now.
We can't get supplies in, products can't get out to market.
Often the power and the water run along that road, so now the community hasn't got
electricity or the wastewater treatment plants aren't working or they haven't got
water. And so the reason that we thought about that both is to
focus on where are the greatest risks we want to manage, but also where
are the best intervention points.
So then if we think about if we can make that road network resilient,
we can reduce those risks to those communities on the other side as well.
So when we think about where you prioritize action, where is the best bang for the
buck to think about where we focus.
Next slide, please. And then last point just to note, so
as Joe said,
as well as those extreme events that we're seeing, it's also those slow
changes. So over time, those increasing emissions are driving up average
temperatures and average rainfall and these sorts of things.
And so those can have really big, widespread consequences.
So it might change growing seasons, it might change what can grow in a certain
area. Or, the heat stress communities are feeling.
It's getting hotter year on year. Anyone that's driven the Devil's Elbow that
melts every summer. That road can handle a certain temperature range.
If the temperatures creep up, that road melts more and more and more, because the
temperatures are higher.
And so some of those changes we can adapt to.
We can add more cooling in urban areas or change the crops that we grow, some of
those sorts of things. But some of those changes we can't actually adapt to.
So levels of sea level rise that erode cliffs that take
away coastal communities, we can't stop that sea rising.
Or changes in ecosystems that mean species don't actually survive, which we're
seeing some of that now with some of our invertebrates and some of our reptiles.
The conditions are changing and those species are at risk.
So
we've got time to see those changes coming, but often it's quite big changes we
need to think about or shifts we need to make.
So having that long horizon for those extremes, but also those
gradual shifts and changes means we can take the
time to plan how we respond.
And with that, Karen, I'll pass to you for the-
Yes. Okay
... the interesting guts of the report.
Yes. So this brings us to the top 10 most significant
risks that we landed on in the National Climate Change Risk Assessment.
So these are the areas where focused action would make the
biggest difference.
So when you look at these risks, some of them are risks that are already
likely to seriously affect people and assets.
Some of them will have serious effects soon, looking out to
2050, and take time to prepare for.
And some of them, if we address these, will have benefits
downstream because it reduces the risk to communities and the economy.
So what you'll see here is that many of these significant risks
relate to the systems that support people's quality of life and
economic resilience.
They're essentially the core systems that we rely on to
keep daily life running. So our water infrastructure,
the buildings we live in,
transport networks,
the natural environment on which
sectors of our economy rely, emergency management,
community wellbeing, and the way we make decisions and fund
adaptation and response.
Next slide, please.
So the National Risk Assessment, is at a
national level,
but at the same time, we do get information through on that on
what that might mean across the country.
And, so we thought it would be useful to share some of this.
We do actually have a detailed piece of work coming out
that looks more regionally. Or yeah,
different districts around the country.
That will be coming out in a couple of weeks' time.
So this is a little bit, sharing some of that, in
advance.
So this map-
I presume Northland will feature in your new next round of
data.
Oh, I thought it was. Oh, this is just a flood of this new-
Well, we had a bit of that too.
Because that's on the next map.
On the next, yeah.
It doesn't get better.
Yeah. Very important.
Thank you.
Post on the new year.
Look weird that.
Yeah. Yeah. That's the next one.
We're-
Not inland flooding.
We're happy to share-
Get that too
... data that goes-
Not as much
... district by district, if that would be helpful.
Yeah.
So this, this map here shows people, homes, and roads
currently exposed to inland flooding.
And so inland flooding is the flooding that, that occurs when heavy rain
overwhelms our stormwater systems or when rivers breach their banks.
Mm.
And this shows a one in 100 year event.
Oh, okay.
So at a national level,
the exposure is already substantial.
Around 560,000 buildings are already
exposed. Around 250,000
of those are homes. And just to put that in
context, approximately 4% of those households are currently
unable to obtain insurance quotes from two or more-
Mm.
Um, underwriters.
What you can see in this map is the exposure isn't distributed
evenly. So if you look at Wairoa, Kawerau,
and, um, Buller, they have the highest proportions of people in
homes exposed to inland flooding.
Urban districts, like Auckland, Christchurch, and Lower Hutt, have
lower proportions but higher absolute numbers.
So,
about 43,000 homes, um, in Auckland.
Yeah, it's a city, wasn't it?
Mm. City impact.
Mm.
So as MPs, you'll see firsthand
how, um, the, the flow and effects that storms
cause to inland flooding. And not just inland flooding, but landslides and silt
deposition. And this is only showing you that inland flooding picture.
So the issue, as Grant talked to, it's not just around damage to
properties. It's how that impacts communities and the economy.
Um, people being displaced from their homes, um, in some cases
permanently.
Mm.
Businesses, health services, and schools being disrupted.
Um, and then of course the recovery costs that that places
on, um, households, councils, um, and central
government.
Sorry, just a question on this. Is this just a snapshot as in
real time now?
Currently.
Have you got any data in this which shows the variations over, like-
Absolutely
... 20 years?
Absolutely. So, um, and just to give you a little bit of context,
so I said 250,000 homes currently
exposed at a national level. By 2050, that would increase to
about 270,000, and we can certainly break that
down, um, by different location as well.
Thank you.
Yeah. For different scenarios and, um, different time periods.
Um, but I guess what this map really illustrates is why
buildings are one of the top risks that, um, comes through on the
risk assessment and just the, um, if we can address risk to
buildings, it can help with those flow on economic and social
consequences.
Um, next slide, please.
So this map is, um, similar type of analysis, but this is for
coastal flooding.
Um, and what I'd really like to hone in on here, um,
is on roads.
Um, so when roads fail-
Mm
... the effects, um, ripple far beyond-
Yeah
... the transport system.
Even a very small percentage of network damage, um, can cause
major financial, um, and social consequences-
Yep
... whether that's from coastal flooding or landslips.
Um,
and I think there's a couple of examples of that in Northland with the Mangamuka
Gorge and-
Mm
... the Brynderwyns, which are, yeah, both very good examples of that.
Um, and-
That's true
... both part of State Highway 1 as well.
Mm.
So at the national level here, about 1% of our roads are
currently exposed to coastal flooding.
Um, that approximately doubles with 50 centimeters of sea level
rise. Um, and you'll be able to see that the proportion of
roads exposed in some places is higher.
So, um, Kaipara and Napier, uh, have higher
proportions there.
When you say how important a road that exposed to this, is that the coastal when
the sea level rise, because the roads are at low level, okay.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
Understood.
And the proportion of the total roads in that district.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah. Um, so today, about, um, 32,000 people
are directly exposed to coastal flooding.
But around 142,000 could become
isolated, um, if important services, um-
Mm
... from important services if the coastal flooding cuts them off by road.
So that's more than four times, um, the number of people that could be isolated
than directly exposed.
Um, just honing in on Thames-Coromandel, I think that's a
useful example here. Um, only 3% of the roads and 6%
of the population there are currently directly exposed, but about
half of that population could be cut off, um, just from
coastal flooding alone.
Mm.
So that shows the importance of those roads for being able to get around.
Um, when we look at businesses, we see a similar pattern.
So nationally, around twice as many businesses are likely to be cut
off as are directly exposed to coastal flooding.
Um, and when we, when we look at that even more closely, that's
particularly an issue for agriculture, forestry, and fishing
businesses, um, which of course has, um, big
consequences, um, given the need to get perishable goods
to market, um, in a timely fashion.
So what, what this really illustrates is why roads, um,
uh, emerged as one of the most significant risks in the risk assessment as well.
Um, next slide, please.
And so moving on to the too little water side of the
equation. So these maps show the annual potential
evapotranspiration deficit,
and that essentially tells us about how dry soils could
be in the future.
So this is an indicator of the potential for drought.
So the darker the red in these maps, the greater the moisture
deficit is.
On the left is our low scenario that Grant talked to, and on the right is the high
scenario.
East coast is the place to be.
Yeah.
So-
There is a lot of rain
In some way.
I was hoping to show-
South.
Is that per year millimeters?
Yes.
Millimeters of rain that didn't fall.
It's broader than rain. It's moisture in the soil, so it
factors in rainfall, but it also factors in-
Evapotranspiration.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
And temperature over time as well, and how that changes.
Over the last, yeah.
And just to know, Karen, that's change from current conditions, isn't it?
Yes. Change from current.
So that's the increase in the deficit with, from, if you're
already actually dry in an area or relatively wet, that's the sort of the relative
change.
It would be a lot worse.
Yeah.
I was, yeah. Unfortunately, we're just showing you 2050 here, but we
can share the 2030 and the 2090 maps with you as
well. But what this shows is that the already
drought-prone northern and eastern coasts of both islands
are projected to get drier.
So just to put this in context, under the low scenario on the
left there, about a third of New Zealand's production
land could become markedly drier
by 2050. So that's where the deficit is greater than 50
millimeters.
And under the high scenario, that would be about half of our
production land.
So the importance of irrigation as well.
Yeah.
So droughts obviously can have a very severe impact for
our agricultural and horticultural sectors.
Just to put that in context, the drought in 2013 that
affected the entire North Island and parts of the South Island
was estimated to be $1.5 billion
economic loss. So that's significant.
I wasn't born yet, so.
In the risk assessment, where we landed was that
pastoral agriculture and horticulture sectors are currently
coping reasonably well.
However, there is a step change looking out to 2050 as climate change
impacts intensify. So the risks
to pastoral agriculture and horticulture sectors are ones that
we need to watch.
So just on that,
you mentioned food security. Like, you touch on it-
Mm-hmm
... but it's not sort of highlighted as one of the key
risks or anything.
Is that something that you're assessing isn't
of extreme risk to the country? I'm just noting, for example, the
UK had their threat assessment, and climate change and
biodiversity loss was absolutely pivotal in terms of their water and
food security. Is it less of a issue for
New Zealand at the moment?
So food security can show up in certain ways when it
comes to that community perspective.
And we've seen that when we've visited places
like Northland.
Mm-hmm.
In terms of what we're looking at here, impacts on pastoral agriculture
and horticulture, it's more about
risks
to crop yields,
impacts on animals from warmer temperatures,
that kind of thing that we're looking at, and then how that might flow on to
impact people.
Mm-hmm.
I think the food security question does also become a question about
what we produce in New Zealand.
Yeah, so it's a broader question than that.
Yeah. But, I mean, it's not like you did a fulsome assessment and then
determined that it wasn't a risk, or
is it that you just haven't really extended your risk
assessment
that far?
So we
don't--
So in the risk assessment, we considered 40 odd risks, and there isn't a
specific risk to food security considered within that.
We do think about it a bit in terms of the
community well-being risk.
Okay.
Yeah. Carrying on, please. Can we just sort of shuffle through this?
Yeah.
We haven't got long to go, have we?
Said to Joe.
Yeah. It's just everyone else was asking questions.
No, that's all right. No.
No, I haven't actually, no.
No, no.
Sorry. I mean, on that slide.
No. It's all right.
Carry on.
Well, I did have some final slides, but I wonder actually in the
interest of giving a chance for people to ask any-
Is there any other key point you want to make?
I think very quickly,
the risk assessment is part of a policy cycle.
The next steps are with government to, um,
uh, con-
Yeah
... reflect the 10 significant risks in the National Adaptation Plan.
Commission has that monitoring role of the National
Adaptation Plan. And
you'll be seeing our adaptation progress report in a few
weeks. There were, on my last slide, there were a couple of points I
wanted to make. First,
delay is not neutral.
So waiting
has a consequence as much as acting.
Mm.
That these risks cannot be managed in isolation.
So a really key point is there is no one ministerial portfolio that
covers all these risks.
Mm.
They cross portfolios, and so that means there
needs to be a broader response.
The timing really matters here.
Climate change is not going to line up neatly with budget
cycles, electoral terms, asset life
replacement. So it may mean that there are decisions with
long lead times that may feel premature, but actually we need to be thinking
about right now.
Okay.
And those are probably the key points. I'm going to stop, let you talk.
All right. I'll start with Rachel because she's next to primary, then I'll go to,
um-
That Deborah and them will work down.
Okay.
And I might slip one in there soon.
Great. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Unsurprisingly to no one, I'm interested in resource management reforms.
And,
you've talked about we can't just do business as usual on hazards, and
then you're saying that it's a whole lot more than one portfolio.
Obviously,
resource management is important in terms of what
is allowed to go where, and we should have some spatial planning, and all of the
information here will be helpful for that.
But do you think,
if you were writing resource management laws,
what would you be doing in that hazards
area?
Well, first, to put some caveats around this.
Yeah. Which is very fair.
The risk assessment doesn't go into policy.
And of course, the detailed policy is-
Yeah
... for the government. We will be having our
adaptation assessment monitoring report coming out in a few
weeks, that is going to dive a lot more-
Okay
... into the gaps in the fundamental system.
So I really want to put that caveat around it.
Yeah.
But then I'll pass to Karen, if there's any further comments around
resource management that you want to make.
Yeah, I guess maybe the one thing I'd add is,
in just seeing the changes that are coming through, or proposed
with the Climate Change Response Act, for city and
district councils to have a role in adaptation
planning. I guess the one thing to say is,
it's absolutely vital to have more planning.
The gap that we see in New Zealand and internationally is in that implementation
space. And-
Right
... so there is a big funding
and financing question.
Yeah.
That is the challenge.
And also there's always those two different things in
a resource management sense of activities that are
already in place that are going to be affected by a hazard, and
things that don't yet exist-
Mm
... that you can stop in an area that you're going
to know is hazard prone. So I'm more interested in that latter piece, because
I know that there's this other work and the
existing activities is much more difficult.
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
You know?
Mm-hmm.
In terms of policy.
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
But that second piece, in terms of things that
will become
hazards. Do you have any thoughts on that?
Predicting it. Yeah. I think probably best not to get ahead of the-
Yeah, so the report's coming out in the next few weeks.
I think we've got another slot with the committee to
present on that, so we can happily go into more detail there when we've got our
latest work. Thanks.
Thank you. Right, Deborah.
One straightforward one. The Climate Change Response Amendment Bill that's
currently in front of the House. Were you consulted on the adaptation work in that?
No.
In terms of your modeling that you've done,
you've used
a low scenario of SSP1 to 2.6 and a
high scenario of SSP3 to 7.0.
Correct.
But we've already passed one degree,
and passed 1.5. So in a sense, that
low scenario has been wiped out a bit now.
So I'm just curious as to why you went with...
Is that just in the way you've reported it to us, or have you also worked on that
medium scenario as well, the SSP2 to 4.5?
So that low scenario, that RCP1, 2.6-
Yeah
... that's around 2 degrees of warming by the end of the century.
So that's acknowledging that that 1.5 is gone.
It's looking at,
sort of, really strong coordinated efforts could still limit us to around 2
degrees by the end of the century. So that was the low ambitious one we used.
Yeah.
So yeah, not tying to 1.5. It's around 2 degrees of warming by the end of the
century. So we used
that one.
Look, I guess the worry is sitting in that all the adaptation work we
need to do, we need to be looking at
what's realistically going to
be available to us, and just as the top extreme has come down, the bottom
extreme is lost.
Mm-hmm.
So it's a little bit unrealistic to have that low one sitting in there.
I don't know what to do about that. But, yeah.
But having something that's bottomed out at one, so SS-
Oh, sorry. Yeah.
Is it confusion?
Sorry.
I think we might have some conf-
So the-
Yeah
... those numbers don't necessarily mean...
So the SSP1 means it's scenario group one,
and the 2.6 means that's how much energy
per square meter is packed. So-
Okay. Got it
... that nomenclature-
Thank you
... what that means is around 2 degrees of warming by the end of the century.
Great.
Sorry. Yes.
So the low and the, yep, that's all good then.
We didn't name them. They are confusing numbers.
No, I appreciate that. So thank you for clearing that.
Right.
Just one last question.
And I've got heaps of things I'd love to ask, but-
I know
... have you-
I'm sure you have.
We're starting to see the possibilities of hot bulb moments
appearing overseas.
What, sorry?
Hot bulb.
Hot bulb moments.
Ugh.
In the what?
Where the temperature and-
You mean like in Europe, ma'am? That we talked about.
No, that's not the same. The hot bulb is where the temperature and the humidity
is such that a human being cannot sweat enough to cool their body down.
Okay.
And so people die.
Thank you for defining it.
Yeah.
Sort of.
Is that one of the future risks we might encounter here in New
Zealand, or is that something floating through your thinking at various places?
You've probably, you've been touching some of it today.
Yeah. And of course, we're seeing a lot of heat waves at the moment in the Northern
Hemisphere.
Yes.
When it comes to hazards in New Zealand, inland flooding
is probably the most-
Sure
... important one to focus on.
Yeah.
Heat, we don't quite have in the same context as other countries.
Doesn't mean we shouldn't be thinking about it.
Yeah.
We have actually done some work to start thinking about it a bit differently.
So with heat, it's really important to think about it in the context,
in a locational context,
additional warming for somewhere in New Zealand.
Will have a very different impact for additional warming that you'd see
in warm parts of Australia, for example, where homes are built
for those temperatures. So we're doing some work to think about it more in
the
how might the top 2% of hot days
increase over time and they could well double,
looking out to 2050.
Yeah, I'm just thinking in terms of we're getting increased moisture and increased
heat, which is,
the Waikato-
That little hot box. Hot bulb
Hot bulb. B-U-L-B, like a light bulb.
Okay. Thank you.
It's actually a serious-
Oh, sorry. Rachel's got a sup on this, then I'll come to you.
Just a little sup, which-
Rachel
... at the talking about scenarios, and also going back to my questions about
planning.
We've had the Minister for Local Government write to councils
saying to use, not use one scenario and to
not
be overly-
Pessimistic
... dramatic about what could happen.
But you're telling us
we need to do more than business as usual in terms of hazards.
And then flooding is a real problem.
Yeah.
And these hot days are going to be a problem as well.
Do you have a view on the letter that the minister sent?
And do you know what I'm talking about?
Sorry, I don't know-
Yeah, we're aware of that
letter. And of course, NFE produces guidance for councils.
That's not the Commission's-
Yeah
... role. So we're in a separate space to
that. I think
Grant touched on
some of this
when he was talking about the scenarios-
Yes
... and needing to consider a range-
Range
... of scenarios when you're making planning decisions.
Yes. That-
That's really important because of that uncertainty
... picture advice. Yeah.
So you have a range, and the range is important, and you can talk about different
trigger points for-
Yes, exactly
... you might know when you get to-
Exactly. Yeah
... which scenario you're actually going to be in.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Celia, and then I-
Actually, very quick question on the heat side of things.
Has your modeling included the amount of extra energy we're going to
need if everyone decides that they need air conditioning and things like that?
Hospitals will need more air conditioning and so forth.
Does that factor in?
So that might be a question that's relevant for our emissions monitoring report.
Right.
Not this risk assessment.
Not so much the adaptive .
Yeah.
Okay. And the other one was, for the different reports, but
particularly this one,
how
content have you been with the reporting in the media about
these reports? Do you think there's been sufficient
attention? Do you think they've picked out the right things
or,
I mean, is it where you get this burst of attention, and then it just goes back
to not mentioning it?
The
media reporting is important because that's how a lot of people get information
about the-
Yeah
... work we do. We don't primarily have an educational role.
We're actually here primarily to advise government-
Yeah
... and be transparent around that.
So,
there has been a lot of media
coverage of-
Yeah
... the different aspects of the report, and I think that's been a really healthy-
... thing.
And we've also had a lot of follow-up
requests for engagements. We're talking to lots of different business sectors-
That's good
... different communities and councils off the back of these reports, which I
think is a really important thing, that that conversation is really picking
up. And people are looking at that independent evidence base to
help them determine
their choices.
Thank you.
Okay, Bec. Right. I'll have a couple of questions if you don't mind.
The adaptions,
as I alluded to it before, the importance of
creating more water storage so that
farming systems can, A, maintain where they are, and without even talking about
increasing-
Mm-hmm
... areas, is just maintain. On the Hawkesbury, is probably a classic example of
that. But how important is it to actually think in those
terms, but not only in terms of
having water to meet the crops growing, that sort of stuff,
but also,
in terms of flood prevention, to control water flows and that sort of thing,
because they act as a retention dam.
Any comments on what are your thoughts on that?
Yeah, we think about water security, that in the
framework-
Mm
... of water security, in terms of
the
droughts that we're going to face in the future.
That's going to be a really important part of the planning.
Yep.
And exactly like you said, it's thinking about actually making sure
that we're building in buffers for our
primary production, our horticulture, et cetera.
And the populations.
And the populations. Yeah, exactly.
And then there's a particular link to
horticulture, cropping.
They are low emissions land uses, are potentially
a place that we can reduce our emissions.
So we need to, at the same time, make sure that there is sufficient
water resource there to actually maintain that industry.
So that's an important part. In terms of the flooding and
maintenance-
Retention dam approach
... yeah, I mean, that's really important.
The first thing is to stay on top of maintenance.
Yeah.
Point is the degree of change that is coming-
Mm
... we need much more than that as well.
No, I appreciate that.
But definitely doing the basics well. Yeah.
But the retention dams do play a part in terms of controlling flood flow.
Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah. I see what you mean. Yeah.
Thank you. Lan, yes.
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks particularly for the table to summarize
how serious these risks are. And I'm
noting, in the policy readiness, there are just
insufficient or significant or extreme
shortfalls in terms of being prepared.
Was there any consideration about- Some kind of
financial assessment, for example, the Parliamentary Commission
for the Environment does an assessment of environmental expenditure across
agencies.
Is that somewhere where this report could get to, to
help
us understand what the magnitude of these gaps
actually might look like financially?
Yeah.
So I don't know that it was considered explicitly here, but
in our adaptation monitoring role, one of the things that we look at there
is implementation of the policies and programs that are
outlined in the government's national adaptation plan, and
funding is one element within that.
So that will come out in a few weeks.
Okay. But in your current processes, there's
no current attempt to try
analyze a financial aspect to any of this?
Well, there are financial aspects that come through the assessment, but this is a
strategic assessment at a national level-
Yes, rather knows
... that implementation part of our adaptation will
come through in the report that's coming out.
Cool. Thank you.
Yeah. Actually, one final question, since it's the last one.
The importance of roading and connectivity, particularly to regional communities.
Yeah.
And so the importance of actually,
roads, like
we talk about the roads of national significance, but I'm thinking particularly in
Northland about a new road out of the Durwans and
the new highway through the Dome Valley, which
closes periodically, causing issues for our communities.
So what you're saying is those sorts of investments are vital for that
connectivity and resilience going forward.
What we've highlighted is the importance of
maintaining connectivity.
Mm-hmm.
There is going to have to be prioritization.
And that is
the details to be worked through at that local level, and
by
the government of the day.
So we don't go to that level of-
Mm
... assessing which road's where.
But highlighting the knock-on
consequences to communities, to the local economy,
and
society more generally when people are cut off for
long periods of time.
Yeah. Thank you. Okay, it's
our time. Thank you very much. Appreciate it .
We're going to have a 10-minute break team.
There's some-
Thank you
... there's some food there if you'd-